A Guide to the Silas Weir Mitchell Collection
University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, #6337-b
Silas Weir Mitchell Collection 1870-1911
University of Virginia. Library. Special Collections Dept. Alderman Library University of Virginia Charlottesville, Virginia 22903 USA
6337-b
ca. 65 items
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Deposit 1963 Dec 17
Item Listing
- Manuscripts
  - Poem, " Friendship ", TMs, 1 p.
  - Westways, n. d.; AMs, 15 p.
    [Early draft of the beginning of
    Westways
    , 1913.]
- Letters
  - Silas Weir Mitchell to Mr. Barney, 1870 Jan 26; ALS, 2 p.
    [Gives thanks for satisfactory closure on sale of land; asks for account of sale of 160 acres.]
  - Silas Weir Mitchell to William B. Dayton, 1870 Mar 3; ALS, 1 p.
    [Encloses account for consultations.]
  - Silas Weir Mitchell to John Cadwalader, 1877 Feb 24; ALS, 3 p.
    [Says he has letter from Cadwalader's grandfather and will keep it for him or send it to him; offers him and his wife money if they need it; offers hospitality in Philadelphia. ]
  - Silas Weir Mitchell to "Dear Madam", 1887 Jul; ALS, 1 p.
    [Responds to request for an autograph; says he is unable to write a selection.]
  - Silas Weir Mitchell to "My Dear Sir", 1890 Jan 23; ALS, 2 p.
    [Gives dates on which he could meet Howard Pyle in New York; discusses a poem and illustration which will appear in a magazine.]
  - Representative of Houghton, Mifflin Co. to H. O. H. and Co., 1892 Oct 25; ANS, 2 p.
    [Informs company that Silas Weir Mitchell approved the page proof; wants manuscript of his preface returned so he may make corrections; encloses a copy of page proof, 3 pages of
    Francis Drake: A Tragedy of the Sea
    includes AN by Silas Weir Mitchell approving the page and requesting the manuscript of the preface for corrections.]
  - Silas Weir Mitchell to Robert Underwood Johnson, 1893 Jan 4; ALS, 4 p.
    [Says he read the book sent to him when he was ill; discusses the merits of poetry and Johnson's, Richard Watson Gilder's, and his own work; promises to send his new book "for revenge."]
  - Silas Weir Mitchell to "Dear Sir", 1897 Nov 20; ALS, 2 p.
    [Says he is willing to read for 20 minutes later on in the program when the audience has quieted down; thinks that too many readers are on the program for the time available; suggests that program be altered because, in its present form, it appears to be a commercial affair.]
  - Lionel A. Tollemache to Silas Weir Mitchell, 1899 Aug 14; ALS, 4 p.
    [Replies to his letter to Beatrice Tollemache; discusses his own writings, especially the character sketches, "talks with Mr. Gladstone," and a small volume sent to Mitchell containing reminiscences of Lewis Carroll; talks at length about poetry, Mitchell's "
    When all the Woods are Green
    "; believes Mitchell's verses are reminiscent of Rudyard Kipling's "
    Recessional Hymn
    "; mentions his schoolfellow, George Trevelyan; refers to a friendly review of
    Characteristics
    in
    The Spectator
    of August 12.]
  - Beatrix Tollemache to Silas Weir Mitchell, 1899 Aug 15; ALS, 4 p.
    [Thanks him for books; mentions
    , "
    , " and her own attempt to write character sketches; discusses an old saying from Cheshire; relates stories about her nephew's exploits in the Rockies and in Africa; tells a story about a Benedictine monk who was sent from England to America. ]
  - Silas Weir Mitchell to Virginia Moore, 1900 Nov 23; ALS, 3 p. w/env
    [Discusses details of speaking engagement at Smith College. ]
  - Silas Weir Mitchell to Centurion, 1906 Oct 27; ALS, 1 p. initialed
    [Responds to inquiry.]
  - Silas Weir Mitchell to Wolcott Gibbs, 1906 Nov 26; TLS, 2 p.
    [Speaks with affection about Gibbs' deceased sister and her hospitality to him; sends him some theses that give evidence of the activity in Smith's department.]
  - Silas Weir Mitchell to [Walter George] Smith, 1908 Jun 4; ALS, 1 p.
    [Responds to request for and autograph.]
  - Silas Weir Mitchell to Miss Belton, 1908 Dec 10; TLS, 2 p. w/env
    [Regrets that he is unable to attend the funeral of his old friend; promises to write again in a few days; sends regards to Emily Tuckerman. ]
  - Silas Weir Mitchell to Miss Belton, 1908 Dec 15; ALS, 3 p. w/env
    [Expresses feelings on the death of her uncle; fears the slow decay of old age; talks affectionately about [ Oliver Wolcott Gibbs], his old friend.]
  - Silas Weir Mitchell to Joseph A. Stetson, 1909 Feb 11; TLS, 1 p.
    [Praises Arthur Hale as a proper member of the Players; says he cannot promise to autograph book because he may not be in New York for months.]
  - Silas Weir Mitchell to Walter George Smith, 1909 Feb 18; AN, 1 p. w/env
    [Expresses thanks.]
  - Silas Weir Mitchell to Walter George Smith, 1909 Mar 3; TLS, 1 p.
    [Remarks on the sonnets of the "Wingless Hours" by an unnamed author he sent to him; believes the author to be an invalid lacking in self-criticism; comments that he himself does not know how to use the "terrible" sonnet form.]
  - Silas Weir Mitchell to William Morton Payne, 1911 Apr 15; TLS, 2 p.
    [Gives him the times he can see him in Chicago; asks to see some people while there as well as Payne's museum in the Park; requests hotel arrangements for himself and his valet; declines a fee; AN accepts cost of travel and hotel only.]
  - Silas Weir Mitchell to Rev. Frank B. Reazer, 1912 Mar 25; TLS, 1 p.
    [Thanks him for an encouraging letter concerning "his best work"; believes that although the book did not sell as well as others, there were rewards of another nature; mentions the many letters from people with similar histories who came to him; singles out letter of woman who told about the influence of drink on her husband.]
  - Silas Weir Mitchell to Francis F. Browne, [ca. 1890] Dec 24; ALS, 3 p. w/env
    [Says he is glad to receive
    The Dial
    wishes that magazine luck, larger space, and competent length of reviews; believes that reviews ought to be signed by the reviewers; speculates that George E. B. Saintsbury wrote an article on "Chicago Fair"; calls S[aintsbury] "really a pestilent fellow"; recommends that Browne reprint Saintsbury's article on Lowell and the Civil War which Saintsbury called "a parochial disturbance"; praises H. B. Fuller's
    The Cliff Dwellers
    . ] (Includes 2 typed carbon copies)
  - Silas Weir Mitchell to William Morton Payne, [ca 1911] May; ALS, 3 p.
    [Wonders about the rooms that were engaged for them in Chicago; sends a list of people he wants to see, especially Dr. Billings and [Patriott]; hopes a lot of doctors will attend his lecture; promises it will be brilliant and original; asks for travel expenses only because he never takes a fee for lectures.]
  - Silas Weir Mitchell to Countess Iddesleigh, Jul 5; ALS, 2 p.
    [Sends her one of his books, which was very successful in America; speaks about a young man he felt sorry for but was unable to help.]
  - Silas Weir Mitchell to "Dear Sir", Oct 4; ALS, 3 p.
    [Says he will send out invitations later than the correspondent will send his announcements; believes Professor Barker will be more helpful than Wood.]
  - Silas Weir Mitchell to "Dear Sir", Oct 5; ALS, 2 p.
    [Requests 2 copies of
    Hephzibah Guiness
    for minor corrections; says no corrections are needed for
    Wear and Tear
    asks that he find the number of editors and the publisher of the first edition of
    . ]
  - Silas Weir Mitchell to Newbold, Nov; ALS, 2 p.
    [Complains that he finds the commercial side of his life distasteful; insists that his own doctor take fees; sends him his consultant account.]
  - Silas Weir Mitchell to [Thomas Bailey?] Aldrich, n. d.; ALS, 4 p.
    [States that Aldrich has recovered from illness and has returned to making verse about Longfellow; says he is working on the third copy of his new novel which will appear next November in
    The Century
    mentions that [Richard Watson] Gilder is excited about the novel; believes it to be a good sign in an editor; refers to his son's new play.]
  - Silas Weir Mitchell to Rofe Cholim, n. d.; ALS, 2 p.
    [Expresses interest and comments on book Cholim sent to him on Cholim's "race."]
  - Silas Weir Mitchell to "Dear Sir", n. d.; ALS, 1 p.
    [Remarks that a book presented to Thomas Jefferson would be worth more if it has Jefferson's signature.]
  - Silas Weir Mitchell to Miss Forbes, n. d.; ALS, 2 p.
    [Advises her to go without Bismuth for some time; recommends four books to be read to her father; mentions a nice note he received from Mrs. Forbes.]
  - Silas Weir Mitchell to Wolcott Gibbs, n. d.; ALS, 4 p.
    [Speaks about telepathic sympathies between them; admires Gibbs' handwriting which belies his age; describes his visits to his patients; notes that he works as a doctor only in the winter and spends summers fishing for salmon and writing fiction in Maine; believes some essential difference exists between scientific work and creative fiction.]
  - Silas Weir Mitchell to Miss Harris, n. d.; ALS, 1 p.
    [Sends regrets because he is unable to undertake "this pleasant and interesting matter."]
  - Silas Weir Mitchell to Mrs. Russell, n. d.; ALS, 4 p.
    [Turns down trip to Buffalo to see a mental patient; discusses the problems of diagnosing and treating mental patients; asks for contribution to enlarge his nervous hospital; reports that Mr. Robb is very well, but unaware of the peril he was in.]
  - Silas Weir Mitchell to Charles Strong, n. d.; ALS, 1 p.
    [Feels that members of the W. Island Club that are not present should be able to vote on new members; thinks it should use the same procedure as in the Round Table Club; suggests that Strong make some change in the laws.]
  - Silas Weir Mitchell to "Dear Ann", n. d.; AN, 2 p. initialed
    [Says number 5-c has been ready for her for awhile; fears that it will be part of a collection nobody will buy.]
- Document
  - Legal agreement for publication of A Christmas Venture, 1908 Jan 29; TDS, 2 p.
    [Signed by Silas Weir Mitchell and George William Jacobs & Co. and witnessed by Cosntance J. Greer and Pariau S. Parsons. ]
- Photograph
  - Magazine reproduction of Silas Weir Mitchell in profile, 1914 [Jan]; Photograph
    [Includes biographical sketch listing Mitchell's accomplishments as a physician and writer
- Miscellaneous
  - Silas Weir Mitchell to Mr. [Dutihl], 1874 Jan 1; Receipt
    [For medical attendance.]
  - " >A Prayer " by Silas Weir Mitchell, n. d.; Broadside
    [Includes 2 copies of a poem.]
  - " Ave Pennsylvania ", n. d.; Leaflet, 3 p.
    [Poem, signed by Silas Weir Mitchell. ]
- Autograph Book
  - "Autographs of Poets", n. d.; AMsS, 45 p.
    [Volume bound in dark blue leather with gilt ornamentation; includes following items.]
  - Robert Browning to Mr. Field, 1883 Feb 8; ALS, 4 p.
    [Reflects on six weeks spent in Venice. ]
  - Henry Wadsworth Longfellow to [ Silas Weir Mitchell], 1866 Dec 13; ALS, 3 p.
    [Thanks him for the book which he is looking forward to reading.]
  - "I see the immediation sweet.. " by Ralph Waldo Emerson, n. d.; AMsS, 1 p.
  - [James] Bayard Taylor to [ John Kearsley Mitchell], 1854 Nov 4; ALS, 4 p.
    [Recommends his brother for the position of physician at Lazarette.]
  - Dante Gabriel Rossetti to "My dear sir", n. d.; ALS, 1 p.
    [Regrets that he cannot help with the binding.]
  - [Fitz-Greene] Halleck to John Kearsley Mitchell, 1840 Feb 26; ALS, 1 p.
    [Declines invitation.]
  - Poem, " Identity " by Thomas Bailey Aldrich, 1905 Mar 19; AMsS, 1 p.
    [Inscribed to Silas Weir Mitchell. ]
  - Oliver Wendell Holmes to [ John Kearsley Mitchell], 1846 Dec 14; ALS, 2 p.
    [Says he is pleased by comment about poem; includes AN on verso, initialed W. M., 1892, describes when Holmes gave Mitchell the poem and letter.]
  - Poem, " Old Ironsides " by Oliver Wendell Holmes, AMsS, 2 p.
  - Francis Scott Key to John Kearsley Mitchell, 1841 Sep 25; ALS, 2 p.
    [Discusses his publishing projects.]
  - [William Cullen] Bryant to John Kearsley Mitchell, 1840 Feb 26; ALS, 1 p.
  - Poem, " Lincoln " by James Whitcomb Riley, 1905 Feb 12; Broadside
    [Includes signed autograph dedication to Silas Weir Mitchell. ]
  - Florence Marion Howe Hall to Mrs. Mitchell, Jul 11; ALS, 2 p.
    [Asks her to send copy of "
    Battle Hymn of the Republic
    . "]
  - Florence Marion Howe Hall to [Silas Weir] Mitchell, Jul 16; ALS, 4 p.
    [Encloses autograph copy of "
    "; claims share of credit for writing it since her mother wrote while staying with her; compliments his book.]
  - Poem, " Battle Hymn of the Republic " by Julia Ward Howe, n. d.; AMsS, 3 p.
  - Poems, " Hymn of the Marches " and " Individuality " by Sidney Lanier, AMsS, 7 p.
    [Signed by author.]
  - Poem, " Chopion " by [Helen] Grace Smith, n. d.; AMsS, 1 p.
  - Printed poem, " On a soldier fallen in the Phillippines " by William Vaughn Moody, n. d.; Clipping
  - Fragment of poem, "From the forest down to the river were ten broad ditches or more,.. ." by Carl Benson( Charles Astor Bristed), Aug 7; AMsS, 3 p
  - List of words or terms regarding Morris-dancing, n. d.; AMs
    [Laid in back of volume.]
  - Printed card for Social Art Club Dinner, Sep 16; Printed Card
    [Includes 17 autographs, 10 identifiable as Moncure Daniel Conway, John W. [Karlson], Stanley Matthews, Andrew D. White, Weir Mitchell, E. R. Robinson, [ J. F. Davies], James MacAlister, George Sechel Pepper, William Pepper. ]